Anthony Lewis Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Anthony Lewis Papers 1941-2007 1963-2001
MSS75856
Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013
347,000 items
998 containers plus 1 classified
399.0 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Newspaper columnist and author. Correspondence, memoranda, book drafts, research files for books, notebooks and notes, articles and columns by Lewis, reports, speeches, newsletters, photographs, press releases, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and other material documenting primarily Lewis’s professional activities.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Russell, 1925-2019--Correspondence.; Burgess, Anthony, 1917-1993.; Bush, George W. (George Walker), 1946-; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Fortas, Abe, 1910-1982--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Correspondence.; George-Brown, George Alfred Brown, Baron, 1914-1985.; Gideon, Clarence Earl--Correspondence.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997--Correspondence.; Halberstam, David--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Kissinger, Henry, 1923-2023--Correspondence.; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987--Correspondence.; Le Carré, John, 1931- --Correspondence.; Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013.; Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013. Gideon's trumpet. 1964.; Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013. Make no law: the Sullivan case and the First Amendment. 1991.; Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013. Portrait of a decade; the second American revolution. 1964.; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003--Correspondence.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990--Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald.; Reston, James, 1909-1995--Correspondence.; Spock, Benjamin, 1903-1998--Correspondence.; Sulzberger, Arthur Ochs, 1926-2012--Correspondence.; Wilson, Harold, 1916-1995.; Wofford, Harris--Correspondence.
Organizations
Columbia University--Faculty.; European Economic Community--Great Britain.; Great Britain. Army.; Harvard University--Faculty.; United States. Constitution. 1st Amendment.; United States. Department of Justice.; United States. Supreme Court.; Yale University--Faculty.
Subjects
Abortion.; Afghan War, 2001-2021.; African Americans--Civil rights.; American newspapers--England.; American newspapers--United States.; Apartheid--South Africa.; Apportionment (Election law)--United States.; Architecture.; Bombing, Aerial--Cambodia.; Busing for school integration--United States.; Capital punishment.; Civil rights.; Concorde (Jet transports); Courts--United States.; Crime--United States.; Drug abuse and crime--United States.; Emigration and immigration--United States.; Energy policy--United States.; Freedom of speech--United States.; Habeas corpus--United States.; Human rights.; Iran-Contra Affair, 1985-1990.; Iraq War, 2003-2011.; Journalism, Legal--United States.; Journalism--England.; Journalism--United States.; Law--United States.; Libel and slander--United States.; Medical care--United States.; Medicine--United States.; Natural resources--United States.; Political corruption--United States.; Political violence--Northern Ireland.; Power resources--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election.; Press.; Race relations.; Right to counsel--United States.; Royal houses--Great Britain.; School integration--United States.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Student movements--United States.; Students--United States--Political activity.; Terrorism--United States.; Terrorism.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; War on Terrorism, 2001-2009.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.
Places
Africa--History.; Cambodia--History.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; Latin America--History.; Middle East--History.; Northern Ireland--History--1968-1998.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Foreign relations--1989-; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1989-; United States--Social conditions--1945-; Yugoslavia--History--20th century.
Titles
New York times.
Occupations
Authors.; Journalists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Anthony Lewis, newspaper columnist and author, were deposited in the Library of Congress by Lewis in 1977. In 2002 Lewis donated the collection to the Library. Material received between 1977 and 1979 were processed as Part I of the papers. Several additions were sent to the Library between 2002 and 2008 and were processed as Part II.
Transfers
Sound recordings and videotapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Anthony Lewis Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Anthony Lewis are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1927, Mar. 27 Born, New York, N.Y.
1948 A.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1948 1952 Deskman, Sunday Department, New York Times
1951 Married Linda Rannells (divorced)
1952 Staff, National Democratic Committee
1952 1955 Reporter, Washington Daily News
1955 1964 Reporter, Washington Bureau, New York Times
1955 Received the Heywood Broun Award and Pulitzer Prize for national reporting
1956 1957 Nieman Fellow, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1963 Received Pulitzer Prize for national reporting
1964 Published Gideon's Trumpet. New York: Random House Published Portrait of a Decade: The Second American Revolution. New York: Random House
1965 1972 Chief, London, England, Bureau, New York Times
1969 2001 Columnist, New York Times
1974 1989 Lecturer on law, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1983 2013 James Madison Visiting Professor, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1984 Married Margaret H. Marshall
1991 Published Make No Law: The Sullivan Case and the First Amendment. New York: Random House
2001 Received Presidential Citizens' Medal Editor, Written into History: Pulitzer Prize Reporting of the Twentieth Century from the New York Times. New York: Henry Holt
2013, Mar. 25 Died, Cambridge, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Joseph Anthony Lewis (1927-2013) span the years 1941-2007, with the bulk of material dating from 1963 to 2001. The papers document primarily Lewis’s career as a newspaper reporter and columnist for the New York Times and his work as an author of several books about legal issues. In 1963 Lewis won a Pulitzer Prize for his reporting about the Supreme Court and is credited with changing the field of legal journalism. Although not a lawyer, Lewis had a grasp of the complexities of the law and a clear writing style that made legal issues more understandable to the public. The collection consists of two parts with some topics and time periods common to both parts. Part I consists chiefly of drafts and research files for two of Lewis’s books, Gideon’s Trumpet (1964) and Portrait of a Decade (1964), and letters from readers of Lewis’s New York Times column between 1969 and 1975. Part II makes up the bulk of the collection and pertains chiefly to Lewis’s tenure while a reporter and columnist with the New York Times from 1955 to 2001. Also included in Part II are files relating to his endeavors as a university lecturer and his writings, including drafts of articles, book drafts, and research files. The papers contain only a few items relating to Lewis’s career before 1955. The collection is in English.
Part I
Part I of the Lewis Papers spans the years 1941-1975, with the bulk of material produced from 1963 to 1974. Drafts, research files, and letters from readers of Lewis's New York Times column between 1969 and 1975 are organized into three series: Subject File, Letters from Readers, and Writings.
The Letters from Readers series comprises the largest part of Part I. Lewis's staff organized most of the letters he received between 1969 and July 1973 into a topical file and those received after July 1973 into a chronological file. The series provides insight into public opinion during a politically and socially turbulent era. Most of the letters were written by the general public and concern issues such as busing for racial integration of schools, medicine and health care, student protests, the Vietnam War, and Watergate. Prominent correspondents include Hubert H. Humphrey on busing; Allen Ginsberg on crime and drugs; general comments by David Halberstam and Daniel P. Moynihan; and Alfred M. Landon, John Le Carré, Lewis Mumford, and Benjamin Spock on Vietnam. Lewis's replies to these letters are included in the series.
The Writings series contains drafts and research files for two of Lewis's books. In Gideon's Trumpet, he explored the Supreme Court ruling in Gideon v. Wainwright that required states to provide indigent criminal defendants with free counsel. Research for the book includes copies of letters between Clarence Earl Gideon, Abe Fortas, and the court; correspondence and documents concerning amicus curiae briefs filed by various states; correspondence with lawyers representing Gideon in his second trial; and a survey of state public defender programs. In Portrait of a Decade, Lewis traced the civil rights movement from 1954 to 1964 largely through the New York Times reporting of these events. Although the research files consist primarily of clippings, they also contain correspondence and an unsigned letter from Harris Wofford concerning his role in arranging John F. Kennedy's phone call to Coretta Scott King in November 1960.
The collection also contains a small Subject File comprising research material for some of Lewis's articles.
Part II
Part II of the Lewis Papers spans from 1944-2007, with the bulk of material dating from 1964 to 2001. Papers in this addition supplement Part I of the collection. The majority of the papers in Part II document Lewis’s career with the New York Times from 1955 to 2001. Lewis reported and commented for over five decades on many prominent issues relating to national and international affairs, including civil rights, the press, the Supreme Court and various legal issues, the Vietnam War, the Watergate scandal, the Iran-Contra Affair, the Middle East, the apartheid regime in South Africa, immigration, and terrorism. Also represented in Part II are teaching files pertaining to university classes that Lewis taught about legal issues and journalism, book files, and a few family papers. The papers of Part II are arranged into the following series: Annual File, Letters from Readers, Writings, Notebooks, Miscellany, and Classified.
The Annual File in Part II, 1949-2007, includes correspondence, subject files, interviews, notes, reports, newspaper clippings, and speeches and writings by Lewis. It is the largest series and focuses mainly on his tenure as a reporter and columnist for the New York Times from 1955 until his retirement in 2001. Papers in the Annual File, dating from 1955 to 1964, document Lewis’s reporting for the Washington, D.C., bureau where he covered the Department of Justice and the Supreme Court and includes files about various justices and Lewis’s notes for the October 1963 and 1964 terms. Other topics treated during his time in Washington are civil rights, reapportionment, and habeas corpus. Also chronicled in the Annual File is Lewis’s tenure as chief of the London, England, bureau from 1965 to 1972. Lewis’s reporting from London varied widely with coverage of politicians such as Harold Wilson and Baron George Alfred Brown and topics such as architecture, Anthony Burgess (writer), the Concorde, and the royal family. The London files also include topics that featured prominently in later columns by Lewis such as, Africa, the Vietnam War, the press, and race relations. Drafts of his “London weekender articles” are filed in Part II of the Writings series.
In 1969 while still in London, Lewis began a column for the New York Times that would later be entitled “At Home Abroad” or “Abroad at Home” (depending on his location) about national and international affairs. In 1973 Lewis returned to the United States, writing the column from his home in Boston. Many of the columns reflected Lewis’s interest in the law and his belief in its importance to a diverse country such as the United States. Lewis brought a liberal perspective to his column on a wide-range of issues such as the energy crisis in the 1970s, immigration, courts, the Supreme Court, the environment (filed as surroundings), capital punishment, the press (especially libel issues), free speech, civil liberties, human rights, terrorism, presidential administrations and elections, the Iran-Contra Affair, Watergate, Latin America, the Middle East, the Vietnam War, Africa, the struggle against apartheid in South Africa, and the unrest in Yugoslavia during the 1990s. Files from 2001 to 2007 reflect Lewis’s interest and thoughts about the reaction of government leaders to the September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks, the ensuing wars in Afghanistan and Iraq, and the War on Terrorism.
The Annual File is arranged by year except for the first group of files from 1949 to 1965 which were filed together as a group by Lewis. Annual File topics "A-L" for 1966 were not received by the Library. Items from a prior Annual File year are occasionally carried over to the next year. Also some years of the Annual File contain background information items that are dated earlier than the year in which they are filed. The majority of the papers in the Annual File were used by Lewis as background research for his reporting and columns. Lewis, however, also traveled to gather information for his articles and columns. The Annual File is replete with trip files, particularly for Africa, the Middle East, and Vietnam, documenting Lewis’s insights. Information relating to his trips is also chronicled in Part II of the Notebooks series.
The Annual File also documents Lewis’s correspondence with an array of individuals including colleagues, Supreme Court justices, judges, lawyers, members of Congress, government officials, academics, entertainers, friends, and the public. The bulk of the correspondence, usually including both incoming and outgoing, features praise by Lewis relating to an achievement by a correspondent or vice-versa. Most of the letters are filed in the miscellaneous folders located after topics in the Annual File. Also documented in the Annual File are invitations and arrangements for social engagements. Correspondents include Russell Baker, Felix Frankfurter, Anna Freud, Henry Kissinger, James Reston, and Arthur Ochs Sulzberger.
The Letters from Readers series in Part II complements the Letters from Readers in Part I. This series includes incoming letters, usually accompanied by Lewis’s outgoing replies. The incoming letters are usually a one-time response to Lewis’s articles and commentary, although the letters do feature recurring correspondents. Topics represented are the Middle East, Cambodia, the Vietnam War, South Africa, abortion, race, immigration, the environment (filed under surroundings by Lewis and his staff), Jimmy Carter, Ronald Reagan, Bill Clinton, George W. Bush, and political conflict in Yugoslavia during the 1990s.
The Writings in Part II are comprised chiefly of drafts of Lewis’s “London weekender articles,” and files relating to several of Lewis’s books. Most of the book files pertain to Make No Law: The Sullivan Case and the First Amendment in which Lewis examines the issues of freedom of speech, libel, and the press in the Supreme Court case New York Times v. Sullivan. Other writings by Lewis are located in Part II of the Annual File, especially the byline folders and topical files. Some proposed books and a few books authored by Lewis were also filed in the Annual File by Lewis’s staff. Files pertaining to Gideon’s Trumpet occur throughout the Annual File. Years after its publication, Lewis still received correspondence about the book. Papers in 1979 and 1980 Annual File contain files relating to a movie based on Gideon’s Trumpet.
The Notebooks series documents many of Lewis’s endeavors as a reporter and columnist from 1974 to 1999. The Notebooks from his London bureau tenure, 1965-1972, cover a wide range of topics such as the beginning of the political violence in Northern Ireland, the British entry into the European Economic Community (EEC), the withdrawal of British forces abroad, and the relationship between the United States and Great Britain. The Notebooks include Lewis’s interviews of people from Northern Ireland regarding the Irish Republican Army bombings and the policies of the Democratic Unionists Party. Also represented in the series are the British Parliament’s discussions on withdrawing forces from territories east of Suez and military forces which were a part of the British Army of the Rhine. Other notebooks chronicle the parliamentary discussions about the involvement of the United States in the Vietnam War and the bombing of Cambodia. Notebooks from 1973 to 1999 document mainly Lewis’s many trips to London, Africa, and the Middle East. One 1973 notebook contains notes relating to Watergate.
The Miscellany series consists chiefly of files pertaining to Lewis’s teaching files about legal issues and journalism. The majority of the teaching files document Lewis’s lectures at Harvard Law School, Columbia University, and Yale University. This series also includes appointment books, photographs, and a few family papers.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in nine series in two parts:
Part I: Subject File, 1962-1973
Part I: Letters from Readers, 1969-1975
Part I: Writings, 1941-1964
Part II: Annual File, 1949-2007
Part II: Letters from Readers, 1957-2001
Part II: Writings, 1944-2007
Part II: Notebooks, 1964-1999
Part II: Miscellany, 1967-2006
Part II: Classified, 1968-2003
Container List
- Part I: Subject File, 1962-1973 (Box I:1-2)
  Clippings, correspondence, speeches, reports, press releases, notes, and photographs used in research for Lewis's newspaper columns.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - America, 1962, 1970 (Box I:1)
  - Architecture, 1970 (Box I:1)
  - The arts, 1969 (Box I:1)
  - Biafra, 1969 (Box I:1)
  - Crime, British and American, 1969-1970 (Box I:1)
  - Defense and foreign policy, 1969-1970 (Box I:1)
  - Disarmament, 1969, undated (Box I:1)
  - Housing, 1969-1970 (Box I:1)
  - Medicine, 1970-1973 (Box I:1)
  - Noise, 1970 (Box I:1)
  - Privacy, 1969 (Box I:1)
  - Salmon fishing, 1968-1970 (Box I:1)
  - "Surroundings," environmental issues, 1969-1972, (2 folders) (Box I:2)
  - Youth and morals, 1969, undated (Box I:2)
- Part I: Letters from Readers, 1969-1975 (Box I:2-16)
  Letters from readers of Lewis's columns, accompanied in most cases by copies of his replies.
  Arranged in a chronological and a topical file.
  - Chronological file (Box I:2)
    - May 1970-Oct. 1972, (4 folders) (Box I:2)
    - Oct. 1972-Nov. 1973, (7 folders) (Box I:3)
    - Nov. 1973-Jan. 1974, (6 folders) (Box I:4)
    - Feb.-Apr. 1974, (5 folders) (Box I:5)
    - Apr.-Aug. 1974, (7 folders) (Box I:6)
    - Aug.-Nov. 1974, (6 folders) (Box I:7)
    - Nov. 1974-Jan. 1975, undated, (4 folders) (Box I:8)
  - Topical file (Box I:8)
    - Africa, 1970-1972 (Box I:8)
    - Agnew, Spiro T., 1970, (2 folders) (Box I:8)
    - The arts, 1970-1971 (Box I:9)
    - Black, Hugo LaFayette, 1970-1972 (Box I:9)
    - British rail, 1970-1971 (Box I:9)
    - Busing, 1972 (Box I:9)
    - Carswell, G. Harrold, 1970 (Box I:9)
    - Crime and drugs, 1970-1973 (Box I:9)
    - Economic and monetary issues, 1970-1972 (Box I:9)
    - Elections, 1970-1972 (Box I:9)
    - England, 1969-1972 (Box I:9)
    - Environment (Box I:9)
      - 1969-1972, (2 folders) (Box I:9)
      - 1972 (Box I:10)
    - Equality, 1972 (Box I:10)
    - Free speech, 1971 (Box I:10)
    - General comments, 1969-1973, undated, (3 folders) (Box I:10)
    - Gideon, Clarence Earl, 1972 (Box I:10)
    - Harlan, John Marshall, 1972-1973 (Box I:10)
    - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., 1969-1973 (Box I:10)
    - India and Pakistan, 1971-1972 (Box I:10)
    - Ireland, 1969-1973, (2 folders) (Box I:10)
    - The Jewish vote, 1972 (Box I:10)
    - Kennedy, John F., 1971 (Box I:10)
    - Kennedy, Robert F., 1969-1973 (Box I:11)
    - Law, 1970-1972 (Box I:11)
    - McGovern, George S., 1972 (Box I:11)
    - Medicine, 1970-1972, (3 folders) (Box I:11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box I:11)
      - A-N, 1969-1973, (3 folders) (Box I:11)
      - P-Y, 1969-1973, (2 folders) (Box I:12)
    - Nixon, Richard M., 1971-1972 (Box I:12)
    - Noise, 1969-1971 (Box I:12)
    - Obscenity, 1970-1971 (Box I:12)
    - Privacy, 1969-1971 (Box I:12)
    - Soviet Union, 1971-1973 (Box I:12)
    - Supersonic airplanes, 1970-1971 (Box I:12)
    - Supreme Court, 1969-1972 (Box I:12)
    - Taxes, 1969 (Box I:12)
    - Vietnam (Box I:12)
      - Oct. 1969-May 1970, (2 folders) (Box I:12)
      - July 1970-May 1972, (7 folders) (Box I:13)
      - June-Dec. 1972, (6 folders) (Box I:14)
      - Jan.-July 1973, (4 folders) (Box I:15)
    - Violence, 1969-1972 (Box I:15)
    - Watergate, 1973, (3 folders) (Box I:15)
    - Wilson, Harold, 1971-1972 (Box I:16)
    - Young, Michael, 1971 (Box I:16)
- Part I: Writings, 1941-1964 (Box I:16-21)
  Drafts, correspondence, and research files for Gideon's Trumpet and Portrait of a Decade.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material under each title.
  - Gideon's Trumpet (Box I:16)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box I:16)
    - Draft, 1963, (3 folders) (Box I:16)
    - Research (Box I:16)
      - Betts v. Brady, 1941-1942, 1962 (Box I:16)
      - Gideon v. Wainwright, 1962-1963, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box I:16, Box I:17)
      - Notes, 1963, undated, (2 folders) (Box I:17)
      - Public defender programs, 1963, (2 folders) (Box I:17)
      - Second trial, 1963 (Box I:17)
      - Writings and speeches by Lewis and others, 1961-1963, undated, (2 folders) (Box I:17)
  - Portrait of a Decade (Box I:18)
    - Draft, 1964, (5 folders) (Box I:18)
    - Miscellany, 1963-1964, undated (Box I:18)
    - Research (Box I:18)
      - Chapter 1, 1944-1963, undated, (2 folders) (Box I:18)
      - Chapters 2-7, 1952-1964, undated, (9 folders) (Box I:19)
      - Chapters 8-12, 1956-1964, undated, (10 folders) (Box I:20)
      - Chapter 13, 1958-1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box I:21)
- Part II: Annual File, 1949-2007 (Box II:1-843)
  Correspondence, memoranda, notebooks and notes, articles and columns by Lewis, reports, interviews, speeches, newsletters, photographs, press releases, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and other material documenting Lewis's professional activities.
  Arranged chronologically by year, although files from 1952-1965 are filed as one group, and therein alphabetically by name of organization or person, topic, or type of material.
  - 1949-1965 (Box II:1)
    - Administrative law
    - American Bar Association
    - American Law Institute
    - Antitrust
    - "A" miscellaneous
    - Biographical information and photographs
    - Bylines, (4 folders)
    - "B" miscellaneous
    - Capitol
    - Civil rights, (3 folders) (Box II:2)
    - Congratulatory correspondence for assignment as bureau chief, London, England
    - Courts, (2 folders)
    - "C-D" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - Expense sheets
    - "E" miscellaneous
    - Fair trade
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation
    - "F" miscellaneous